Hello, and welcome back to another
episode with ItsDrDan, and today
we're going to be learning about
the basics of nuclear chemistry.
So with nuclear chemistry, what
this is all about is an unstable
nucleus that is decaying.
It's falling apart.
Maybe it's going through all
kinds of different reactions.
So today we're going to be mainly
focusing on how this is breaking
apart and some of the different types
of nuclear equations that you could
possibly see and how to balance them.
So, when we go through this, we're going
to go through the definitions, the four
different types of particles that you're
going to see, and we'll go through the
tips and tricks on how to balance these.
Let's go take a look at how these types
of little unstable nuclei, like the one we
see here, how it's going to break apart.
All right,
so the basic idea of radioactivity,
it comes from when unstable nuclei,
when they're ready to break apart.
It's like taking a Lego sculpture
and smashing it against the wall.
It could break apart in all
kinds of different ways.
Now these are mainly found in atomic
nuclei that are generally higher than 20.
And that's because the more protons that
we have in the nucleus, like the one that
is drawn all the way up top here, right?
Like the one here, it has a lot
of protons, a lot of neutrons,
protons in red, neutrons in blue.
Now, the more of these that you
add, their protons are going to
start repelling each other, right?
Like charges, they don't like
being near each other, so they
get a little bit unstable.
So when that happens they can
break apart and as a result when
they do break apart they can emit
all kinds of different radiation.
So they can be in the form of what we
call alpha particles, beta particles,
positrons, or gamma ray emissions.
Now, when this is released, this could
have a huge effect, something that
could be used in the medical industry.
It could be something that's
found in the world around us.
It could be used in all kinds of different
applications or for energy, you name it.
Now, when these happen, this is
a way for these atoms for them
or isotopes to relax back down.
So it ultimately, it's going to help it
become more stable when it does that.
So let's take a look at
the four different types.
More in depth.
So what this is all gonna start with
is starting with the radioisotope Which
is just a normal isotope that we've
seen since general chemistry and if you
need some help with that refer back to
my videos on how we can look at atomic
masses counting protons and neutrons
and Looking at our atomic numbers.
So with here, right all these
different isotopes exist for an
element We're going to be showing
that with a whole atomic mass number.
So this is going to be one that's going
to be emitting radiation Now, there
could be more than one isotope for every
single one of these elements, right?
They, if you look at your periodic
table, this is an average.
So I would recommend having your
periodic table handy, either on as
a side window or in front of you, so
that way when we're doing the examples
together, you can follow along.
So the different types, like I
mentioned before, there are four major
types that we're going to be seeing.
Each one of them has a different
representation, so I would recommend
writing each one of these down because
you need to know them in order to
balance the different equations.
So, the very first one
is an alpha particle.
This is the heaviest out of
all of them because this is
represented with a helium atom.
It's equivalent of two protons and two
neutrons breaking off of a nucleus.
Now with this thing, as you can
kind of imagine, it's a very slow
moving particle because it's bigger.
But even though it's slower,
it can do a lot of damage if
it's on the inside of you.
Let's say if you ingest it, it's
not going to be able to get out.
It's something that is
very, very dangerous.
So we write that as a helium atom.
The next one is a beta particle.
This is a high energy electron.
So typically we write this as a
negative one in the atomic number spot.
And electrons, if you remember,
have an atomic mass of about zero.
So we put zero here and we just
use the E to represent electron.
Now, don't get this confused with
the third one, which is a positron.
Positrons and beta particles are
written very similarly to one another.
Beta particles, what we just talked
about, is a negative particle.
Positrons, think of the name positive,
is a positive molecule, or not
molecule, electron in this case.
So when we talk about the positron,
this is referred to as a positron.
Antimatter, meaning the way that we
show this is a plus one next to the E.
So we write a beta plus for this
electron versus the other one we
would show a, um, the electron with
a negative one on the other side.
Now, the last thing that we're going
to have for our last one is the gamma
ray, which is on the very bottom here.
The gamma ray is a pure form of energy
that all it is, is just a release.
So when this happens, this could
be something used for chemotherapy.
It could be used to try to destroy
certain things may be found in the body.
Um, it is just pure energy.
How do we use these?
We're going to learn how to
balance chemical reactions.
We're going to go through the steps
and I'm going to go and review some
different tips as we go through.
Balancing an example
for each one of these.
Now these are really important reactions.
Understand the basics for people in
radiation technology, or anyone interested
in maybe in the medical field, um, or if
you're just interested in basic chemistry.
So I'd really pay attention and take some
really good notes as we move forward.
Okay.
With balancing nuclear equations,
the big thing with these is when
we're balancing 'em, it's way easier
than balancing a chemical reaction.
The idea is, is what
goes in must come out.
If you remember the law of mass
composition, so what you have on the
left side, let's say in the reactants,
must be the same side on the right
side of the products, it's gonna be
the same thing here, but instead,
all's we're gonna be doing is adding
up the sum of the atomic masses.
and the sum of the atomic numbers.
They got to be equal
on the left and right.
So let's go through some examples and
show what this is all about when I say
it has to be equal on the left and right.
So make sure you have your periodic tables
because that's what's going to help.
So with the first one, we're
going to be doing uranium.
So it says Uranium 238, so when we
write this down, what we need to do
is fill in all the little blanks, and
it's going to be an alpha particle.
So the way I like to show these is, if you
remember, every one of them has an atomic
number, they also have a mass number.
So we have a spot for both of those.
Now, the next thing we need
to do is identify what type
of emission process is it.
This one's alpha.
So if you can kind of remember, all
right, we had the four particles earlier.
Alpha was represented by a helium atom,
so we'd put that four, the two, and
we'd show that Now when something's
going into a decay, it's going to
be breaking apart this nucleus, and
it's gonna be turning from a parent
nuclei into a daughter nuclei.
meaning we're going to break
apart even further and make a
new nucleus when this happens.
So when we have this, we are going to
have something that's brand new being
created on the right side as a product.
So now before we can do this, we need
to know what uranium's atomic number is.
And if you look it up on the periodic
table, You'll see it has a mass of 92.
So we'll fill it in our first box.
Before I mention what is on the left
side must equal what is on the right.
We have our left and
then we have our right.
So reactants must equal products.
So on the bottom here, this has
to have a total of 92 because we
have 92 on the left hand side.
So what is 2 plus x?
How do you get 92?
Well, 2 plus 90 is going to be 92.
So we'll fill that in, right?
We'll put the 90.
Now the same idea for
what's on top over here.
This has to equal to 238.
The sums have to be equal.
So what's 4 plus x to get to 238?
That's 234.
So we'll take 234 plus 4, that equals 238.
So what element is number 90, right?
If you remember, this number is
like a fingerprint for how to
determine all the different unknown
elements that are out there.
So when we take our periodic
table, we'll look up what the
atomic number is for number 90.
And what you're going to see
is that this one is thorium.
So this is how you balance it, right?
We have the same amount of mass on the
right hand side as we do on the left.
And we're going to do this
for each individual one.
The hardest part is
remembering the four particles.
Can you add?
We can all add.
Right?
We can go through those basic steps.
So let's take a look at the next one.
Let's do another one together.
This question is what is the
alpha decay of americium 241?
Generally a lot of these problems
are just given just a name.
So what do we have to do is we
got to set up the problem, right?
We have Americium 241.
We need to know what the number is.
So when we look it up in the
periodic table, you'll quickly
see that the number is 95.
So remember that atomic number is, is
the same no matter what isotope it is.
They all have that atomic number of 95.
Mass might be different
from your periodic table.
That doesn't matter because
we're referring to this specific
isotope So the first thing is
what is our it's an alpha decay.
So we're gonna write a helium Now the
next thing what we're gonna do is we
got to fill in the little boxes So
what is what is going to be created?
Well, the mass has to be a
total of 241 and then the atomic
number has to be a total of 95.
So let's start with the atomic mass.
So if we have our atomic
mass, how do we get to 241?
Well we need 4 plus 237 on top.
That's how you equal 241.
Now how do you get to,
uh, 95 on the bottom?
Well, we're going to add
that to ninety three.
All right.
So now what do we do is we got to look
up what is number ninety three on our
periodic table and what you are going to
quickly find is that this is neptunium.
So when this radioactive decay happens
or this alpha decay, when this nuclei
breaks apart, it's going to make a
new element of neptunium, which will
be a slightly more stable nucleus and
this reaction could keep going for
until it eventually becomes stable.
That's the ultimate goal.
Let's go on to the next one.
Okay, let's write an equation for
the beta decay of 40 of potassium 42.
So with K 42, how would we show this?
Well, being that we have our
following element, we would
write down our elemental, our
atomic number, our atomic mass.
And we're going to show how
this is going to break down.
Now with beta decay, how is that
one different than alpha decay?
Well, it was zero negative one is equal
equivalent to an electron breaking off.
So a high energy electron.
Now the math for this is going
to be a little bit different.
So what's on top has to equal to 42 and
what's on the bottom has to equal to 19.
Now the thing is we're adding
a negative number in here.
So how do we get to 19 with a negative?
Well, if we do 20 plus negative
1, that's going to equal 19.
And then on top, we'll have
42, so 0 plus 42 is still 42.
So what element would we
have that is not, is 20?
Uh, so we'd go through our periodic table,
you'd see quickly that calcium is your 42.
Now, can beta decay only happen this way?
Well, with any of these different, uh,
different processes, they can either
be fission, which is breaking apart
or fusion, which is coming together.
So we've been showing decay, which
is all about how things are going or
breaking and going through fission.
Fusion is when we want
to bring them together.
So you could show the opposite.
Which is, let's say if I
want to capture an electron.
So being that, if you think of
K42, 19, and I want to capture an
electron, or in this case a beta
particle, how would this change?
Well, it's going to be the
same general idea, right?
We want to write our little boxes,
and how much, whatever the total
is on the left, has to equal
what the total is on the right.
So we can see we have 42 and 18.
These are gonna be the numbers
that we're going to be filling in.
So then what are we gonna do here is
we're gonna look up atomic number 18 on
your periodic table, and you're gonna
quickly see that this is going to be
argon, which is the answer for this one.
So then that's beta decay.
Let's take a look at the
last two different reactions.
Now, the easiest one that we can
really see is gamma radiation,
which, why is that one easier, right?
We're just adding up the sums.
What this one is, is energy is
emitted from a unstable nucleus,
so it's just pure energy.
The way that we show this is whenever it's
referring to a gamma radiation problem,
you can see that there is a little M
written next to the 99 or the mass.
This is telling you it's metastable and
something that's going to break apart.
Well, gamma radiation is,
is shown as 0 0 gamma.
So we need to make sure the same thing
on the left is what's equal to the right.
Meaning that it's still going to be 99
43 technetium, but we get rid of the M.
So, and that's an example of gamma.
Gamma, it's the same element in the
end, it's the same radioisotope, but
it loses its energy in the form of,
you know, electromagnetic radiation.
This could be used maybe in the form of
chemotherapy or generally something to
really destroy something very harmful.
Uh, so let's go on to our last examples.
Alright, let's write the nuclear equation
for the positron emission of manganese 49.
So with this one, right, when we want
to show manganese, we would still
go through the exact same process
that we've been going through,
but it's talking about a positron.
So emission is all about breaking apart,
so when we show that, that positron coming
off, Right, we show a zero plus one.
It's also very common to show
it as a zero with a beta with a
positive next to it, input plus one.
So either or can be
used in these problems.
It all depends on kind of where
you're learning it and really
what your field of study is, but
they both are applicable here.
I like using both.
So same premise as before, right?
What's on top mu, or what's on
the left must equal the right?
So being that we have a mass total
of 49, on the left hand side,
we have to have a total of 25
for our, for our atomic number.
So what we can see quickly, right?
If I do 24 plus one, that
will equal 25 and on top.
When I do 49 plus zero, that'll equal 49.
So which element would be number 24?
This would be chromium, and that
would be the answer for that.
Now the last part that I'll talk about
positrons is, what about protons?
How could they decay?
Let's look at a more theoretical one.
So protons can be shown two ways.
They can either be represented as a,
as the letter P, where we show one as
the atomic number and, or sorry, atomic
mass, and one for the atomic number,
being that there's only a proton, right?
There's no nucleus.
This is the same thing as representing
a hydrogen, which if you think on your
periodic table has the number one as
the atomic mass and the atomic number.
So you can use either.
Now, if I wanted to say, hey, how is this
going to break apart as a positron decay?
Well, how do we show it?
Well, zero plus one, and
let's do the beta symbol.
How would we balance
the top and the bottom?
Well, remember what's on the left
must equal what's on the right.
And you can already see, well, the
bottom is equal, so this has to be a
zero, and what's on top has to be a one.
What particle has an atomic mass of
one and no, no, um, no atomic number?
What could that possibly be?
That's none of the alpha, none
of the particles we went through,
none of the four, but it is
a subatomic particle, right?
Protons have a mass of one.
So do neutrons.
So this is a neutron.
So when a proton goes through positron
decay, this makes a neutron, right?
So you can have either protons or you can
have neutrons, which can be both be shown.
So I would write that down showing how
neutrons are a particle, because a lot
of nuclear reactions can break apart
a neutron or be bombarded or collided
with a neutron to combine with them.
So there's all kinds
of different reactions.
I hope that this video helped you.
This is the basics of nuclear chemistry.
This will help you kind of understand
some of the things that go on in
radiation technology and some future
reactions and future videos to come.
Um, thank you so much for watching and
I hope to see you all in the future.
Bye now.